hi everyone and welcome back
to part two of this series
a quick recap what i did in the last video
is a basic setup of the player's movements
along with some platforms on the
scene today we'll be expanding on
this to make the camera follow the player
around so that we could explore the level
but before that we will
fix a type of mistake first
now create a script called camera controller
with a public transform variable
called target and the camera reference
to make the camera follow the player
you might think that you could
just directly assign the target's
position to the camera's position
however that's not possible as the current
z position is different from the players
furthermore instead of having the player be
in the middle of the screen we usually want
the camera's position to be slightly in
front so that we could see the area ahead
first create new factor 3 call offset and assign
the initial value of negative time for the z-axis
also create a float cost smoothing as we're
going to be using for smooth camera movement
under update create a local variable
for offset this is for changing the
direction of the offset based
on where the player is facing
with the normal offset when the player is moving
right a negative x value while moving left
thereafter click on the vector3
target position which is the
final position that we want the camera to be in
lastly use lub to move the current
position to our targeted position
without smoothing times time.time setting the
speed of the move we're going to delete the oco 2.
at unity you should be able to see
the camera following the player
the only thing is you can also see the
undeveloped of the map to prevent this
we can create camera boundaries to force the
camera to only show the play area that we want
first let's create more platforms so
they have wider space to work with
with that done in the script create a float
called camera distance with a default value
of 10 and a rectangle which are going
to be used to denote the boundaries
at the same time add two vector2 variables for
the minimum and maximum positions of the camera
next create a function called calculate
boundary and call it instead we're going
to use this function to calculate our minimum
and maximum position that the camera can go to
we're going to start by getting
the bottom left and top right of
our screen so that we know how much
of an area our camera is covering
then calculate the half value of our width
and height so that we are getting the center
point of the screen which is also where
the cameras transformed the position lies
lastly to get our camera's
minimum position and head the
half value to the minimum position of the boundary
vice versa for the next position
maximum position minus a half value
of course when creating the boundary we will
want to have visual feedback on what we are doing
however rectangle does not have that functionality
as it only draws the invisible box for us
first we need to distribute ourselves by using
gizmos a unity tool for visual debugging and scene
setup as whatever is that under this function
only shows up in the scene view and not the game
we're going to set the
color of the length to green
before proceeding to use gizmos draw line to
draw a line between two vectors that we have set
in this case we are drawing from the
top left to the top of the boundary
copy and paste this line three more
times and change the position so the
address from the top right to the bottom right
bottom right to the bottom left
and bottom left to the top left
if that we're able to see the outline
of the boundary that we have set
so set the boundary to cover the space
that you wanted to be shown in the game
then we're going to create another function
we should take in our target position
within it we're checking if the position is
outside the boundary and fix it if it is we're
doing it for the exposition first setting the
position to the minimum if below the minimum
x value and setting the position to the
maximum if above the maximum x value
the same applies for the y position
the final position thereafter
now if the bounds width and height are greater
than zero set the target position to the return
value of the function remember to do this
after target position has included the offset
let's test it out
yup everything is working lastly i'm going
to comment on my code for the scripts
so let's clear what each code is doing
i hope everyone enjoyed the video thanks
for watching and see you next time